<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Dawn Team</origin>
            <originator/>
            <pubdate>2016-08-19</pubdate>
            <title>Ceres Dawn FC2 HAMO Global DTM 137m</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>Digital Elevation Model,Grey Scale,Raster Data,Topographic Map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername/>
               <issue>DWNCHSPG_2</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Flagstaff, AZ</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Astrogeology Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://astrogeology.usgs.gov/search/map/ceres_dawn_fc2_hamo_global_dtm_137m</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>[![CDATA[&lt;b&gt;Product Information:&lt;/b&gt;

This digital terrain model (DTM) of Ceres based on the Dawn High Altitude Mapping Orbit (HAMO) Framing Camera 2 (FC2) images and derived by using the stereo photogrammetry (SPG) method.  The HAMO DTM covers approximately 98% of Ceres surface (few permanently shadowed areas near the poles required interpolation).  The DTM has a lateral spacing of ~136.7 meters per pixel (m) (60 pixel/degree) and a vertical accuracy of about 10 m.  A global DTM is provided in an equidistant cylindrical projection and hemispheric DTMs are provided for both polar regions as stereographic projections. The DTMs are formatted as images where the DN values give the height in meters above a reference sphere of 470000.0m (Preusker et al., 2016). 

&lt;b&gt;Mission and Instrument Information:&lt;/b&gt;

The Dawn spacecraft launched on September 25, 2007 onboard a Delta II-Heavy Rocket. The instrument payload consisted of two identical framing cameras (FC1 &amp; FC2), a visible and infrared mapping spectrometer (VIR, and a gamma ray and neutron detector (GRaND).  DAWN is a National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Discovery Program mission managed by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), with the principal investigator and science operations center located at the University of California, Los Angeles. The framing cameras were built by the Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research, with significant contributions by the German Aerospace Center, Institute of Planetary Research (DLR) and in coordination with the Institute of Computer and Communication Network Engineering (Polansky et al., 2016). 

Dawn spacecraft orbited Ceres in a series of science orbits designed to gradually increase the resolution and quality of science measurements as the mission at each target (Vesta &amp; Ceres) progressed. The four science orbits are: rotation characteristic (RC) at 14,000 km, survey at 4,900 km, high altitude mapping orbit (HAMO) 1,950 km, and low altitude mapping orbit (LAMO) 850 km.  HAMO provided the opportunity to collect data for the global topography model by collecting six complete clear-image maps: two at nadir and four at of nadir attitudes (Polansky et al., 2016). 

&lt;b&gt;References:&lt;/b&gt;

Polanskey, C., Joy, S., &amp; Raymond, C. (2016). &lt;em&gt;Dawn Ceres Mission: Science Operations Performance.&lt;/em&gt; Paper presented at the SpaceOps Conference, Daejeon, Korea. &lt;a href='https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2016-2442' target='_blank' &gt;https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2016-2442&lt;/a&gt;

Preusker, F., Scholten, F., Matz, K. D., Elgner, S., Jaumann, R., Roatsch, T., Joy, S. P., Polanskey, C. A., Raymond, C. A., &amp; Russell, C. T. (2016). &lt;em&gt;Dawn at Ceres - Shape model and rotational state.&lt;/em&gt; Paper presented at the 47th Lunar and Planetary Science Conference, Lunar and Planetary Institute, Houston, TX. &lt;a href='http://www.hou.usra.edu/meetings/lpsc2016/pdf/1954.pdf' target='_blank'&gt;http://www.hou.usra.edu/meetings/lpsc2016/pdf/1954.pdf&lt;/a&gt;

Raymond, C. A., Jaumann, R., Nathues, A., Sierks, H., Roatsch, R., Preusker, F., Scholten, F., et al. (2011). The Dawn Topography Investigation. In Russell, C. &amp; Raymond, C. (Eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Dawn Mission to Minor Planets 4 Vesta and 1 Ceres&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 487-510). New York, NY: Springer. &lt;a href='https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4614-4903-4_16' target='_blank'&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4614-4903-4_16&lt;/a&gt; 

Roatsch, T., Kersten, E., Matz, K.-D., Preusker, F., Scholten, F., Jaumann, R., Raymond, C. A., &amp; Russell, C. T. (2016). High-resolution Ceres High Altitude Mapping Orbit Atlas derived from Dawn Framing Camera images. &lt;em&gt;Planetary and Space Sciences, 125,&lt;/em&gt; 103-107. &lt;a href='https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pss.2016.05.011' target='_blank'&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pss.2016.05.011&lt;/a&gt;]]&gt;</abstract>
         <purpose>[![CDATA[Part of the PDS release of Ceres higher level data (Level 2). Ceres Digital Terrain Model - Certified and released with minor liens as of October 11,  2016.

Dawn mission is equipped with two identical framing cameras (FC1 &amp; FC2) which have one clear filter and seven band pass filters. At Ceres,  only the FC2 was used to acquire science images  while the FC1 was held in reserve. Clear filter images which were  taken during HAMO were used to produce a global DTM of the illuminated part of Ceres [Preusker 2016]. Dawn orbited Ceres  during in 6 cycles between August 16 and October 23,  2015 at the HAMO altitude of ~1475 km. A cycle is a single complete mapping of   surface at a fixed attitude (nadir or off-nadir). The framing camera acquired about 2350 clear filter images [Preusker 2016] during the HAMO phase. The images were taken with different viewing angles and  similar illumination conditions by slewing the spacecraft to various off-nadir attitudes. These images are analyzed by using the SPG method [Preusker 2016] to produce the Ceres HAMO DTM.]]&gt;</purpose>
         <supplinf>[![CDATA[http://dawndata.igpp.ucla.edu/, http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0032063312002589]]&gt;</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>2014-12-26</begdate>
               <enddate>2016-04-21</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In Work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc/>
            <eastbc/>
            <northbc/>
            <southbc/>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt/>
            <themekey>Asteroids</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accscope>PDS</accscope>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Please cite authors</useconst>
      <browse>
         <browsen>https://astrogeology.usgs.gov/ckan/dataset/1a165f71-5f31-44b6-b770-63e53b53902e/resource/a407b289-19ab-451d-bd3d-e423b9949a08/download/ceres_dawn_fc_hamo_dtm_dlr_global_1024.jpg</browsen>
      </browse>
      <native>ISIS v3</native>
   </idinfo>
   <cntinfo>
      <cntorgp>
         <cntorg>USGS Astrogeology Science Center</cntorg>
      </cntorgp>
      <cntaddr>
         <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
         <address>2255 N. Gemini Drive</address>
         <city>Flagstaff</city>
         <state>AZ</state>
         <postal>86001</postal>
      </cntaddr>
      <cntvoice>928-556-7011</cntvoice>
      <cntemail>astroweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr/>
         <logic>The DTMs are formatted as  images where the DN values give the height in meters above a reference sphere of 470000.0m. 

The conversion from Digital Number to PLANETARY_RADIUS in meters is:
PLANETARY_RADIUS = pixel_DN + 470000.0m</logic>
         <complete>There were a few permanently shadowed areas near the poles required interpolation.</complete>
      </attracc>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar/>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>Best Effort</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin/>
                  <pubdate/>
                  <title>Dawn at Ceres - Framing Camera</title>
                  <online>{https://sbn.psi.edu/pds/resource/dawn/dwncfcmosaics.html,https://sbn.psi.edu/pds/archive/maps.html}</online>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc/>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>[![CDATA[The framing camera acquired about 2350 clear filter images [Preusker 2016] during the HAMO phase. The images were taken with different viewing angles and  similar illumination conditions by slewing the spacecraft to various off-nadir attitudes. These images are analyzed by using the SPG method [Preusker 2016] to produce the Ceres HAMO DTM.]]&gt;</procdesc>
            <procdate>2016-08-16</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>10800</rowcount>
         <colcount>21600</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Equirectangular</mapprojn>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>136.7174581</absres>
                  <ordres>136.7174581</ordres>
               </coordrep>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn/>
            <semiaxis>470000</semiaxis>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altdatum/>
         <altres/>
         <altunits>Meters</altunits>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Astrogeology Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>2255 N. Gemini Drive</address>
               <city>Flagstaff</city>
               <state>AZ</state>
               <postal>86001</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>928-556-7011</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>astroweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <diginfo>
               <formname/>
               <transize>446 MB</transize>
            </diginfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>https://astrogeology.usgs.gov/search/map/ceres_dawn_fc2_hamo_global_dtm_137m</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>2025-06-07</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Astrogeology Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>2255 N. Gemini Drive</address>
               <city>Flagstaff</city>
               <state>AZ</state>
               <postal>86001</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>928-556-7011</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>astroweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metsdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metsdn>
      <metstdv>Modifided FGDC standard for use with planetary data</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <metprof>USGS Astrogeology Planetary Geoscience Metadata Standard</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
